1532年 伦敦
London 1532.
- 公爵阁下 - 托马斯大人
- Your Grace - Lord Thomas.
乔普斯大使
Ambassador Chapuys.
我原以为你抛弃了我们
I thought you had abandoned us.
是这样 的确如此
It is truth, I did.
我试过
Or tried to…
只是公平地说 我绝不能抛弃王后陛下
in all conscience, i could never abandon Her Majesty.
她是世上最高尚 最杰出的女人
She is the most gracious and wonderful woman in the world.
却最悲伤
and the sadest.
所见略同
I agree with you.
皇帝陛下同样这么认为
so does the Emperor.
陛下特致您一函鼓励
He has writtend this letter of encouragement…
示意支持
and support…
您为她的奔走效力
for your efforts on her behalf.
我恳求您莫要递交此函给我
I beg you not deliver it to me.
即使我已经对国王
Although that I've given more than sufficient…
显示了足够的忠诚
proof of my loyalty to the king.
须知瓜田李下 不能贻人口实
I must do nothing to provoke suspicions.
考虑到当前所处的环境
Consider the time we live in.
我不能失去可以
I don't want to be deprived of the liberty…
允许我私下对贵上与王后方面事宜
which allows me to speak boldly in private.
建言的自由
About this matters which concern your master and the queen.
明白 不必赘言
I understand, you need say no more.
- 谢谢 克伦威尔先生 - 陛下
- Thanks, Mr. Cromwell. - Your Majesty.
托马斯·莫尔爵士觐见
Sir Thomas More.
克伦威尔
Cromwell.
托马斯·莫尔爵士
Sir Thomas.
国王陛下
Your Majesty.
我得告诉你
I must tell you.
我收到一些众议院议员的陈情
I've received a petition from the members of the House of Commons.
投诉高级教士和教职人员的残忍行为
complaining of the cruel behavior and abuses of the prelates.
和虐刑
and the clergy.
托马斯
Thomas…
臣民们要求摆脱教会统治
people are asking for freedom from clerical rule.
陛下明察
Your Majesty knows…
我一直都谴责教会的虐行
very well that I've always condemned the abuses of.
当这种行为曝光的时候
the clergy. When they have been brought to light.
作为您的首相
As your chancellor,
我不竭余力来消灭这种现象
I have worked hard to eliminate.
净化我们神圣的教会
them and purify our Holy Church.
但是…
But…
您知道我的立场
You know where I stand.
您一直都清楚
You've always known.
我无法宽恕
I cannot condone this.
您基于私人信仰和个人喜好而产生的新观念
new fangled vision of private belief and personal grace.
对我来说 教会是上帝存在的永久象征
For me, the church is the permanent and living sign of God's presence.
它是生灵活现的社团
It is a visible, palpable community.
并非几位教友在密室里的聚会
Not just a few breather and gathered secret rooms.
就是说您会反对我？
Then, you'll speak against me.
我对陛下的热爱和对陛下的忠诚
My loyalty and love for Your Majesty is so great.
使我绝不会在当众反对您的旨意
that I'll never say a word against you in public.
上帝保佑我
So, help me, God.
国会 威斯敏斯特
Parliament Westminster.
国王驾到 全体起立
Arise for the King!
- 陛下 - 陛下
- Majesty. - Majesty.
诸位大人 主教大人们
My Lords, Your Graces.
我们齐聚于此 来听取你们对于
We've come here among you to hear your response.
指控和所肩负的责任的回应
to the charges and responsibilities laid against you.
你们均被控支持前任红衣主教渥西
You're generally charged with supporting the authority of the late Cardinal Wolsey,
和罗马主教 反对你们自己的国王和国家
and the Bishop of Rome, against that of your own king and country.
你们有些人可能觉得我在谋求私利
Some here among you may suppose I seek personal advantage.
事实并非如此
It is not so.
作为国王 我赋有重整世界秩序
As your king, I'm commission to restore right order on Earth.
维护我国疆域完整
and assert the immunities and princely liberties.
王权不受侵犯的责任
of our realm and crown.
这是我神圣的职责
This is my sacred duty.
此乃面对上帝而定
Seal before God,
由我加冕礼的就职宣誓开始
and by solemn oath at my coronation.
渥兰大主教 你们的结论是什么？
What is your conclusion, Archbishop Warham?
陛下
Your Majesty,
在我呈禀之前 我先请最受尊崇的罗彻斯特主教
before I deliver it, I give way to His Grace, the Most Reverend Bishop Fisher,
费施尔主教大人发表意见
The Bishop of Rochester.
各位大人
My Lords,
陛下要求我们确认
we are asked to admit His Majesty.
他为英格兰教会最高领袖
As supreme head of church in England.
不幸的是 要准予国王此职
Unfortunately, we cannot grant this to the king.
就无法不放弃我们与罗马教廷的统一
without abandoning our unity with the See of Rome.
如果我们要断绝与天主教世界的一致
If we are to renounce the unity of the Christian world.
跳下圣彼得的船
and leap out of Peter's ship.
那我们都会淹没在异教邪说
then we shall be drown in the waves of all heresies.
的巨浪中 四分五裂
sects, schisms and divisions.
请恕我直言
I say to you…
认同君权高于我们神圣的教会
that the acceptance of regal supremacy over our holy Church…
将会致使彻底撕裂
would represent a tearing thunder…
基督的无缝外衣
of the seamless coat of Christ.
主教大人
Your Grace.
请给出你们的判决
We will hear your judgement.
我向国会提议
I'll put this proposal to congregation…
国王陛下将被授予新头衔
that Your Majesty has a new title.
「英格兰教会和神职人员的最高领袖」
Supreme head of the Church and clergy of England.
但是我增加了个限制范围
But I add a caveat.
只在基督律法允许范围内
As far as the law of Christ allows.
赞同的？
Those in favor?
很好
Very well.
[拉丁语]无声就是默许
Qui tacet consentire videtur.
沉默就意味着同意
whoever remain silent so they are assumed to agree.
谢谢 主教大人
Thank you, Your Grace.
罗马
Rome.
- 坎佩基奥主教 - 圣父
- Cardinal Campeggio - Holy Father.
坐吧 坎佩基奥主教
Sit down, Cardinal Campeggio.
我知道你患有痛风在身
I know you are on hard to gout.
我的脚也疼死
And my feet are killing me too.
你找我有何贵干？
What do you want to see me about?
我们又收到两封
We have received two new letters…
事关英格兰国王要事的信函
regarding the king of England's great matter.
噢 又是此事
Oh. That again.
他们怎么说？
What did they say?
第一封来自国王本人
Well The first is from King himself…
敦促教廷对他取消婚约做出最终
urging curia to make final and favorable decision…
而且有利的决定 以保护英格兰的和平
on his annulment for the sake of peace in England.
他有几处言辞激烈 教皇陛下
He used some temperate language holiness.
他抱怨「从未有过任何教皇」
Complaining that "never was any prince handled by a Pope…
「如您一般对待我等君王」诸如此类
as your holiness has treated us".
他是指我的前任 坦白讲他没说错
He meant my predecessor, and frankly he has a point.
克莱门特确实过于拖拉
Clement was a terrible procrastinador indeed.
尽管人们不该将他的尸体挖出来
Although it was very wrong for some people to dig out his dead body.
当街凌辱
and stabbed it in the street.
我还是理解那些人的感受
I can well understand that feelings.
他从不被人爱戴
He was never popular.
愿教皇克莱门特的灵魂安息
Requiescat Pope Clement.
第二封信呢？
And second letter?
神圣罗马帝国皇帝寄来的 以他的姑妈
From the emperor, on behalf of his aunt.
凯瑟琳「伤心的王后」的名义
Katherine, the "unhappy" queen.
敦促您制止这婚约的取消
Urging you to prevent the annulment.
并把英国国王逐出教会
and excommunicate the king.
我们必须要作决定
It is true we must come to a judgement.
另一方面
On the other hand.
从保护教会的利益出发
To protect the interests of the Church.
我们要避免顾此失彼得罪任何一方
We should try not to antagonize one par above the other after all.
毕竟他们有士兵和武器
They have soliders and guns.
我们只有美德和真理
whereas we must make duel with beauty and truth.
那个女孩 娼妇 国王的妓女怎么样了
What of this girl, this putain, the King's whore.
安妮·波林
Anne Boleyn.
是的 为什么没人干脆除掉她呢？
Yes, why doesn't someone just get rid of her?
不
No.
不必起来
Don't get up.
就待在哪儿
Stay like that.
你如此美丽
You are so very beautiful.
如此让人向往
So very desirable.
我无法不全然占有你
I have to possess you utterly.
我迫不及待
I can't wait.
我的爱人
My love.
很快
Just a little longer.
到那时再说
And then.
我已成为英格兰教会的最高领袖
I've made the head of the church of England.
真的？
Is it true?
我太开心了
Then I am so glad.
你终于获得自己的权力
At last you have your right.
可以随心所欲
and can do as you will.
我已欣然命克伦威尔粉刷塔里的一些房间
I am glad to have Cromwell refurbish some of the apartments on the tower.
英格兰每任王后加冕前都呆在那
Every queen of England stays there before coronation.
爸爸
Papa.
怎么了？
What's wrong?
你不想庆祝一下吗？
Don't you want to celebrate?
说这话还为时过早
It's far too early for that.
主教们并没有被真正击败
The bishops were not really defeated.
由于默认 投票结果为国王当选教会领袖
By default, they voted to make the king head of the Church.
但「只在基督律法允许范围内」
But only as far as the law of Christ allows.
你不必是个聪明的律师也知道「基督律法」
You don't have to be a clever lawyer to know that the law of Christ.
可以使这次投票结果无效
that may be used to invalidate the vote itself.
这么说一无所获
Then it was all for nothing.
不
No.
并非徒劳
Not for nothing.
法则已经被他们大部分人所认可
The principle has now been effectively conceded by most of them.
乔治告诉我
As George told me.
他们的抵制与反抗只来自一个人
their resistance and the recalcitrance really stemmed from only one man.
- 该死的费施尔主教 - 费施尔？
- that bloody bishop Fisher. - Fisher.
- 先生 - 克朗默先生
- Sir. - Mr. Cranmer.
克伦威尔先生 很抱歉来迟了
I'm so sorry to be late, Mr. Cromwell. That's completely unforgivable.
胡说 我们还没有开宴 见到你很高兴
Nonsence, We haven't even begun to dine. It's good to see you.
波林先生 怀特先生 这是克朗默先生
Mr. Boleyn, Mr. Wyatt, This is Mr Cranmer.
克朗默先生 您是位牧师吧？
Mr. Cranmar, you are a man of the cloth I believe.
您不是位诗人吗 怀特先生？
And are you not a poet? Mr. Waytt.
那才是我最轻浮的一点成就
That's the least of my sense.
晚餐后你可以聆听我的忏悔
You may take my confession after supper.
如果我是你就不听 会让你头发都白了
I wouldn't if I were you. It'll turn your hair white.
你来之前我们正在讨论
We were discussing before you arrived,
主教会议的进展情况
the progress of the Congregation of Bishops,
要决定君权至尊的会议
which was called to decide upon the King's supremacy.
陛下明智的决定任命乔治·波林
His Majesty has wisely decided to appoint George Boleyn here.
与诸位主教进行交涉
to negotiate with Their Graces.
我发现他们大部分人都很善于变通
I found most of them accommodating.
当然 也有数顽固的例外
Of course, there're a few stubborn exceptions.
我猜是费施尔主教
Bishop Fisher, I assume.
是的
True.
我能问下还有别人吗
May I ask who else?
还有大主教本人 渥兰
The archbishop himself. Warren.
这么些年来他一直很圆滑
After years being perfectly pliable,
忽然变得相当强硬
he suddenly become rather intransigent.
因为他年纪大了 距离他迟早要面对
It's because he's old, and consequently, he's closer to his maker,
的造物主越来越近
to whom undue course he must explain himself?
那么我相信 会有一个简单之道
Well, I'm sure that there'll be a simple matter of him to explain.
帮他把教会从迷信
how he helped liberate his church from.
和教会贪婪的宗教谎言中解脱
superstition, religious false of the ecclesiastical greed.
路斯先生？
Mr. Rouss.
是 先生
Yes, sir.
你是个厨师
A cook.
想要做笔交易
buy trade.
是 先生
Yes, sir.
你明白我要你做什么吗？
You understand what's expected of you?
明白 是的
I do, yes.
这来是补偿你的困难
This is for your trouble.
如果你背叛我们
If you betray us,
我会毁掉你整个家族
I'll destroy your entire family.
陛下 这是我常提到的克朗默先生
Majesty, this is Mr. Cranmar, whom I have often spoken.
正是这位克朗默先生首次提出
It was Mr. Cranmer who first spoke to the fact that.
陛下的「要事」是神学问题
Your Majesty's great matter was a theological issue.
而非法律问题
and not legal one.
克朗默先生
Mr. Cranmer.
你是我在所有在世的人中最想见到的一个
I have desire to meet you almost above any person now living.
你是宫里最受欢迎的上宾
You're most welcome here at court.
陛下 我…
Majesty, I…
很有意思
It's funny.
王国中一些最伟大最著名的学者
Some of the greatest and most celebrated minds in my kingdom,
都为此懊恼不已 而你
sweated and struggled over an issue which you,
请原谅我的措辞 一位微贱的牧师
an obscure cleric, if you forgive me,
却能轻松又简单的解决了它
was able to resolve with perfect simplicity and a clarity of mind which.
这真是让他们无地自容
put a mold of shame.
陛下 我…
Majesty, I…
我…
Um… I…
克朗默先生
Mr. Cranmer,
陛下已决定钦点你为他的私人牧师
His Majesty has decided to appoint you his personal chaplain.
我…
I… ah…
你该感谢陛下的恩典
You must thank His Majesty.
当然
Of course.
陛下
Majesty.
不必客气 克朗默先生
You are welcome here, Mr. Cranmer.
克伦威尔先生
Mr. Cromwell.
陛下
Majesty.
干得好克朗默先生 干得好
Well done, Mr. Cranmer, well done.
你娶了你的被监护人
So you married your ward?
她叫什么
What's her name?
凯瑟琳·布洛克
Catherine Brook.
凯瑟琳
Catherine.
为什么找她
Why her?
我爱慕布洛克小姐
I love and admire Miss Brooke.
让我有被母亲关怀的感觉
Reminds me some of my mother.
她多大年纪
How old is she?
十七岁
Seventeen.
有母亲般的…
Some mother.
可怜的凯瑟琳
Poor Catherine.
你无法对一个女人忠诚 查尔斯
You're incapable of fidelity, Charles.
你一直如此
you always have been.
这次不一样
This time is different.
有何不同？
How different?
我也说不清
I don't know.
就是感觉如此
I just feel it.
不仅因为她很漂亮
And it's not just because she's beautiful.
我们真的用心相爱
It's a marriage of true souls.
你应该能明白
Surely you can understand that.
阳光 真讨厌
Oh sun, go away.
永生不要打扰我们
Leave us to our own devices.
我爱你 安妮·波林
I love you. Anne Boleyn.
我会永远这么爱你
and I always will.
永远？
Always?
你怎么能这么说 托马斯
How can you say that, Thomas?
时光流转 命运变迁
No unfortune brings what time changes.
可是我不会改变
Time won't change me.
这个也不会
Or this.
托马斯
Thomas.
安夫人
My lady Anne.
当恭喜您宠幸之甚
You ought to be congratulated for reaching so high.
谢谢你 托马斯
Thank you Thomas.
我不会忘记我们曾经的友谊
I shall never forget that we were once true friends.
噢？
oh?
我倒希望我能忘记
I wish I could forget.
你现在也高升了啊
But I see you are raised too.
偶尔处理点外交 承蒙克伦威尔先生器重
well it is a… sometimes diplomat. Thanks to the patronage of Mr. Cromwell.
我们这些诗人画家偶尔也能出点力
We poets and painters sometimes have our uses.
我想向你引荐一个人
There's someone here I should like you to meet.
安妮·波林夫人 这位是马克·斯米顿
Lady Anne Boleyn, this is Mark Smeaton.
大师级舞蹈家 歌唱家 音乐家
Dancing master, singer, musician.
集各种天赋于一身的全才
and general all-round genius.
斯米顿先生
Mr. Smithen.
他喜欢被简单的称呼为马克
He likes to be called just plain Mark.
他怎么能被简简单单的称呼呢
How could he possiblly be called plain?
夫人
My lady.
荣幸之至
It's a great pleasure.
你会拉小提琴吗
You play the violin?
会的
Indeed.
为我演奏一曲吧
Play me something.
当然
Of course.
教教我好吗
Will you show me?
我非常钦佩阁下在主教会议上的演说
I want to thank you Grace your speech to the congregation.
措辞得体 勇气非凡
It is well said and very brave.
句无虚言
I spoke only truth.
我认为所谓的限制范围
I believe that the caveat.
「基督律法允许的范围」实际上推翻了整个提案
So far as the Law of Chist allows does indeed invalidate the whole bill.
基督率法怎能让一个外人 即使国王
How can the Law of Christ permit a lame man, even the King.
成为教会的领袖呢
to be head of the church.
伺童 我只要一点
Boy, a little for me.
[拉丁语]以圣父 圣子
In nomine Patris, et Filii,
圣灵之名
et Spiritus Sancti.
愿永恒荣耀之王指引我们
Ad caenam vitae aeternae perducat nos.
通往永恒生命的晚宴
Rex aeternae gloriae.
阿门
Amen.
我得问一下 托马斯爵士
I must ask you, Sir. Thomas.
你仍然决意辞职吗
If you still have a mind to resign your office.
那次投票之后 主教大人
After the vote, Your Grace,
我得承认我确实非常想
I must confess I was sorely tempted.
但三思之后
But on reflection.
我希望留下为天主教而战
I'm content to stand in fight for christendom.
这可是个好消息
oh this is excellent news.
就像大主教最终回心转意一样
as indeed is the turning again of the archbishop.
感谢上帝 他还有最后的良知
I thank God that his conscience has finally driven him to.
去谴责国王那些荒唐的把戏
condenm the king's nullity suit.
而且他也表明了他的意愿
and he's stated his intention to.
提案反对目前的法规
oppose the legislation.
这有可能妨碍教会的利益
which might be injurious to the church.
快去叫医生
Get the doctor!
快去叫医生 快
Get the doctor! Quick!
来人啊 快来人啊
Help! Please help!
上帝啊 上帝啊
God! God!
四个人痛苦的死去
Four men died of their pains.
费施尔主教因为食用的汤较少而幸免
Bishop Fisher survived in it because he had too little of the soup.
真的是非常不幸 托马斯爵士
It's very unfortunate, Sir. Thomas.
并不仅仅是不幸 陛下
It's more than a unfortune Your Majesty.
费施尔主教的厨师已被逮捕
Now Fisher's cook has been arrested.
但我必须告知您…
but I must tell you that.
关于密谋毒杀他的凶手身份
rumors abound us to the identities.
已是谣言四起
of those who plotted against him.
谁？
Who?
已查出的有威尔特
Wilcherd's being named.
波林？
Bolena?
正是
Yes.
还有…
And?
Well?
有些人甚至怀疑是安女士
Some people even blamed the Lady Anne.
「有些人」把一切事情都怪罪到她头上
Some people would blame her for everything!
下雨怪她
They would blame her if it rains.
不下雨也怪她
or if the rain fails.
皇后无法生育是她的错
They will blame her for the bareness of the queen.
我爱她也是她的错
And the fact that I love her.
是她使大风吹毁了庄稼
They will blame her for the wind that destroys our crops.
让我们的船沉没于暴风雨中
and the storms that sink our ships.
一切都是安女士的过错
It is all the fault to the Lady Anne.
你呢 托马斯爵士
What about you Sir Thomas?
你也认为她是罪魁祸首吗？
Do you blame her?
你认为是她下毒加害费施尔主教的吗？
Do You think she tried to poison Bishop Fisher?
- 亨利… - 叫我亨利的时代已经过去了
- Henry - The time for Henry is over.
不管主谋是谁
Whoever was to blame.
厨师路斯 参与预谋
the cook, Rouss, tried,
且差一点成功毒死了
blatantly, and almost successfully,
陛下最伟大的公仆之一
to poison to one of Your Majesty's great public servant.
我们神圣教会的主教
the bishop of our Holly Church.
还有我
as well as me.
如果陛下对此事置之不理
Now, if Your Majesty would turn a blind eye to this event.
大家将不得不认为
everyone will be forced to assume.
如此的蓄意谋杀
that the attempted murders were.
是得到陛下许可的
done with your blessing.
伦敦塔
Tower of London.
波林大人
My lord, Bolena.
路斯先生
Mr. Rouss,
这番话我们今天已经问过无数次了
We can go over and over this all day, so,
问你最后一次
One more time.
毒药是谁给你的？
Who gave you the poison?
路斯先生
Mr. Rouss.
过去四年你都勤勤恳恳
It is inconceivable you should.
服侍你主人及其家人
suddenly take it upon yourself.
无法想象你会
to murder your master and his household.
一时兴起想要谋害他们
after serving him so diligently these past four years.
毒药是谁给你的？
Who gave you the poison?
先生 我有三个女儿
Sir, I have three daughters.
这有什么关系吗？
What does that mean?
我希望她们能嫁个好人家
I want them to find good husbands,
但这需要钱
but that takes money.
我们可以用钱交换你的信息
We can pay you for your information.
不必了 先生
No, Sir.
已经有人付过款了
The payment is already made.
交易已经达成了
The account settled.
你是个蠢货
You are a fool.
你也会因此而丧命的
And you will die for it.
你 等一下
You, hold a moment.
这匹麻布要送往何处
Where are you taking this linen?
送到王后陛下哪里
To the Queen's Majesty.
为何？
Why?
为国王陛下缝制衬衣
To make shirts for His Majesty.
这是她的惯例
She always has done.
她仍在为他缝制衬衣？
She still makes his shirts?
是的 安小姐
Yes. Yes, Miss Anne.
甜心
Sweetheart.
你怎么能这样？
How could you?
- 什么事 - 你的衬衣
- What? - Your shirts!
她还在为你缝制衬衣
She still makes your shirts.
你怎么能还让她这么做？
How could you let her?
这事我连想都没想过
I haven't even thought about it.
你跟我说过你们之间
You told me there was nothing.
已不存在任何亲密关系了
intimate between you anymore.
本来就不存在
There isn't.
有什么亲密？
What intimate?
看在上帝的份上 不过就是衬衣而已
They are just shirts for God's sake.
它们不仅仅是衬衣
No they are not just shirts.
它们代表着我和你
They are you and me,
它们也代表着你和她之间的关系
They are you and her!
我不明白
I do not understand.
那你永远都不会明白
Then you won't to.
我们即将结婚 而她还赖在这里
It's so hard when we are to be married.
这算怎么回事
but she's still here!
一段婚姻里容不下三个人
You can't have three people in a marriage,
为何你就是明白不了？
why can't you see that?
而你为何就是不明白
And why can't you understand that.
我还有比衬衣更重要的事情需要考虑
I have more things to think about than my shirts?
国王已同意采用新的酷刑
The king has agreed to a new and harsh.
来对付投毒者
treatment to the poisoners.
他们将被活活煮死
They will be boiled alive.
在这种情况下严惩案犯是英明的决策
He's wise to have dealt with severity in this case.
但他仍旧无法阻止某些人
But he cannot avoid some suspicions.
针对安女士和她父亲的猜疑
At least against the Lady Anne and her father.
我们的的命运均掌握在上帝手中
We are all in the hands of God.
但我担心
But I worry that.
当我毫无用处躺在这里的同时
while I lie here uselessly,
国王可以继续他离婚之事
the king may proceed with his divorce.
因为他已赋予了自己这个权利
since he has given himself the power.
我被告之 在上次会议中
I was told that on the last council.
国王盛怒
the king became angry.
他质问
and demanded to know what would happen.
如果他不顾教皇的批准
if he went ahead anywhere and married Anne.
义无反顾地与安结婚会怎样
without the Pope's permission.
大臣们怎么说？
and what did they say?
只有波林支持他这样做
Only Boleyn supported him.
连他的朋友布兰顿都表示反对
Not even his friend Brandon.
感谢上帝
Thank God.
凯瑟琳
Catherine!
夫君
Husband?
您感觉好点了吗？
How are you feeling?
什么？
what?
他们告诉我你正在遭受牙疼之苦
They told me you have been suffering from a toothache.
我知道那有多疼
which I know it's a terrible pain.
甚至有人说您患了痛风
And someone even said that you have a touch of a gout.
我怎么可能会痛风
of course that I don't have a gout!
我不明白你怎么会听信这种不着边际的谣言
I don't know why even you'd listened to such stupid rumors.
因为我在乎你
Because I care for you.
凯瑟琳
Catherine.
你不用再为我缝制衬衣了
you're going to have to stop making my shirts.
我还以为你喜欢我为你缝制的衬衣
I thought you like the shirts I made for you.
你现在就穿着呢
I see you're wearing one.
- 亨利… - 又怎么了？
- Henry? - What now?
我们的女儿玛丽生病了
Our daughter Maria has been none well.
她已经一连八天粒米未进
She has not kept any food on for eight days now.
您觉得我们应该去看望她吗？
Do you not think we should visit her?
如果你想去看望公主的话你自己去好了
You can go and visit the princess if you like.
然后你就留在那儿吧
And you can stay there.
不管是为了我们的女儿或者任何人
Even not for our daughter nor for anyone.
我绝不舍你而去
would I dream of leaving you.
你知道我的合法地位是在你左右
You know my rightful place is by you side.
恳求上帝的仁慈
I can sign myself to the God's mercy.
上帝保佑你 先生
Bless you, Sir.
告诉我的女儿们我走得很快
Tell my girls I died easily.
没有痛苦
and with no pain.
你要头先进去…
Head first?
还是顺其自然？
Or however it comes?
[拉丁语]无声就是默许
Qui tacet, consentire videtur.
解救我
Save me!
坐
Sit.
你妻子真很漂亮
Your wife looks very beautiful.
你们在一起看起来很幸福
You seem very happy together.
的确如此
Yes, we are.
幸福的婚姻是可遇不可求的
Happy marriage is devoutly something to be wished for.
说到此事
Talking which.
我需要你替我做件事
I need you to do something for me.
阁下
Your Grace?
夫人
Madam.
我需要和王后陛下单独交谈
I need to speak to Your Majesty alone.
国王派你来的？
The King has sent you.
这个时候？什么事？
at this hour? why?
国王希望您能明智抉择
The King asks you to be sensible.
撤销在罗马教廷的上诉
withdraw your appeal to the Rome.
并将此事交由他处理
and entrust your faith with his hands.
他保证不会亏待您
and he promises to be more than generous.
您知道国会正在投票通过赋予他
as you know the parliament now is about to make him supreme supereme.
在俗世及教会里的至高权利
in all matter spiritual as well as temporal.
不行
No.
教皇才享有普世最高的权利
Only the Pope has God's power here on earth.
并象征着永恒的真理
and it's internal truth.
我明白
Yes.
- 但是国王… - 阁下
- But the King - Your Grace.
过去到现在 我将一个女人
I love and have loved His Majesty.
最大的爱情赋予了国王陛下
as much as any woman can love a man.
我不会放弃陪伴他做他妻子的每分每秒
But I would not abort him company as his wife one moment.
我都不会违背我自己的良心
against the voice of my conscience.
我是他真正的妻子
I am his true wife.
你大可以去罗马
Go to Rome if you want.
与众多达官要人去理论
argue it there with lots of important men.
而不是在这里和一个可怜女人争论
instead of here with just one poor woman.
她怎么说？
What did she say?
她说她服从两个至高利益
She said she'll obey Your Majesty and everything.
其他一切皆顺从王意
save her obedience to two higher powers.
哪两个至高利益？
Which two higher powers?
教皇和神圣罗马帝国皇帝？
Pope and the Emperor?
不是
No.
上帝和她的良心
God and her conscience.
乔普斯
Chapuys.
陛下
Majesty.
你可以告诉你的主人…
You can tell your master,
实际上你告诉谁都无所谓
actually you can tell anyone you like.
在这件事上我不会向教皇屈服的
I would never agree to be judged by the Pope in this matter.
我毫不在乎法尼斯威胁逐我出教
and I don't care if Farnese tries to excommunicate me.
他可以在罗马为所欲为
He can do what he likes in Rome.
这里是我说了算
I'll do what I like here.
陛下
Majesty.
还有
and by the way.
欢迎回宫
Welcome back to court.
谢陛下
Majesty.
王后是什么样子的？
How was the queen?
她很漂亮
She was beautiful.
但自从有你之后她似乎是另外世界的事了
But it's like a thing of the other world once I got you.
我记得你曾经对我说…
I remember once you told me that.
也许你难免会让我伤悲
You might sometimes have to make me feel sad.
即使是无心为之
Even if you didn't mean to.
你真的会令我伤心吗？
Are you really going to make me sad?
不会
No.
我对一切神明起誓
I swear to all that is holy.
以一切美好事物的名义
All things worth being good.
对你 我将永远忠诚
To you, I will always be true.
至死不变
Never changing.
如果你不相信 我也不会怪你
I wouldn't blame you if you don't believe me.
你相信我吗？
Do you believe me?
陛下
Majesty.
- 你找我吗？- 安妮
- You're sent for me? - Anne.
明天去打猎如何？
How should you like to go hunting tomorrow?
如陛下所愿
If that is what Your Majesty desires.
我们也许要离开一些时间
We may be away for a while,
探访一些人
visit people,
和他们住上一段时间
stay with them.
陛下 这葫芦里卖的是什么药？
Majesty, what is this all about?
当我们归来时
And when we return,
就只有我们了
We shall be alone.
只有我们
Alone?
你和我
You and I,
在皇宫里
here,
没有了第三者
No third person.
此话当真？
Do you mean it?
我已经谕令凯瑟琳离开
I've already given instructions for Catherine to leave.
天啊
Oh, my god.
你是最开心的吗？
Are you the most happy?
夫君 出了什么事情？
Husband, what is this?
- 我看到了 - 什么？
- I saw it. - What?
- 你看到了什么？- 长久以来
- What did you see? - After a long time…
我知道路德和丁道尔 都是伪先知
I knew Lutheran and Tyndale, false prophet.
那么多的征兆
And so many signs…
我还不明白你在说什么
I still don't understand.
你到底看到了什么？
What is it you've seen?
恶棍 基督的敌人
The Beast. The Antichrist.
他触手可及 爱丽丝
He's near at hand, Alice.
- 记得把新的裙子打包 - 遵命 夫人
- You remember to pack me new skirt? - Yes, Madam.
如此美妙的早晨正适合启程
Beautiful morning for a ride.
非常美妙
Beautiful.
好好照顾她 约翰 你自己也小心些
Be very careful with it, John, on your own.
启驾吧
Let's go.
跟上
Move on.
夫人 秘书官克伦威尔先生前来觐见
My Lady, Mr. Secretary Cromwell is here to see you.
夫人
Madam.
陛下命令您于一个月内离开此地
His Majesty commands that you'll be gone from this place within a month.
下榻于陛下的莫尔宫
and settle at his house in More.
他甚至都不说告别
He did not even say good-bye.
当然 您可以带走所有的女佣和侍从
You are free, of course, to take with your attendance and servants.
无论我到哪里
Wherever I go,
我总是他的妻子
I remain his wife,
我会为他祈祷
and I'll pray for him.
还有… 一件事
There's ah… a further matter.
陛下希望你将属于
His Majesty wishes.
英格兰王后的王室珠宝归还
that you return to him the official jewels of Queen of England.
不
No!
我不会放弃我的合法所有
I'll not give up with these rightfully mine.
去装饰一个让所有天主教徒不齿的女人
to adorn a woman who was the scandal of Christendom.
上帝保佑陛下
Bless Your Majesty.
王后陛下
Your Majesty.
上帝保佑王后陛下 上帝保佑
God bless Your Majesty. God bless you.
谢谢
Thank you.
- 上帝保佑王后陛下 - 谢谢你们
- God bless Your Majesty! - Thank all of you.
受天眷的女士
Blessing Lady.
万众爱戴的王后
Queen of Hearts.
当你回到伦敦时
There will be even greater crowds than this to welcome you…
欢迎的人群会比今天更多
when you return to London.
谁？进来
Yes? Come.
顺利吗？
Well?
陛下 我受命向您传达来自王后的告别
Majesty, I'm asked to pass on a message of farewell from the Queen.
她很遗憾未能与您亲自话别…
She regrets that you did not wish her goodbye,
最后她询问了陛下的健康状况
and she inquires after Your Majesty's health.
告诉王后我不需要她的告别
Tell the Queen! I do not want any her goodbyes,
另外 我无意安慰她
and I do not wish to offer her consolation!
我不在乎她是否问候我健康
I do not care whether she ask after my health or not.
让她别再烦扰 专心做自己的事
Let her stop this, and mind our own business!
- 听明白了吗？- 遵命 陛下
- Do you understand me! - Yes, Your Majesty.
滚出去
Get out!
抱歉
I'm sorry.
不用道歉
Don't apologise.
还能有何不同呢？
How could things be different?
一切都如此美妙
Indeed, everything is beautiful.
难道你不认为？
Don't you think?
一切都很美妙吗
Everything is beautiful?
是的
Yes.
一切都如此美妙
Everything is beautiful.
她是个女巫
She's a witch,
她的命运只配下地狱
who deserves all the fate and to be dispatched to hell.
你会去刺杀安妮女士吗？
And you will assassinate The Lady Anne?
作为国王的近身侍从
Being the closer servant of the King.
我可以做到
I'm in a position to do so.
为了自己的欲望 她引诱蛊惑了他
with her lust She seduced and bewitched him.
他就要背叛自己的合法妻子和神圣教廷
he considers betraying his lawful wife and the Holy Church.
你不能再待在此处了
You must not stay any longer,
我们的祈祷和希望与你同在
but our prayers and hopes go with you.